Amazing Grace is a music, documentary film directed by Alan Elliott.
A behind-the-scenes documentary about the recording of Aretha Franklin's best-selling album finally
sees the light of day more than four decades after the original footage was shot.
Amazing Grace is a 2018 concert film "realized and produced" by Alan Elliott.
The film's footage was shot under the direction of Sydney Pollack, who does not receive directorial credit, just a
"special thanks."  Amazing Grace stars Aretha Franklin recording her 1972 live album of the same name.
It co-stars James Cleveland, Alexander Hamilton, and the Southern
California Community Choir, and features her father C.
The film was not released as scheduled in 1972 due to difficulty in synchronizing
the audio with the visual print, and was relegated to a Warner Bros.
vault until 2007, when producer Alan Elliott purchased the
raw footage and attempted to synchronize it.
The edited footage, 87 minutes in length, was planned for a 2011 release.
However, Franklin sued Elliott for appropriating her likeness
without permission, and the release date passed.
Elliott made another attempt in 2015 to hold the film's premiere at the Telluride Film Festival, at the Toronto International Film
Festival, and at the Chicago International Film Festival, but Franklin sued him again for reasons that have not been revealed.
After Franklin's death in 2018, her family made an arrangement to release the film, which
premiered at Doc NYC in 2018, before being released worldwide on April 5, 2019.
The film has received critical acclaim.
The film explores themes of live performance, concert film, gospel music.